<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An houre glasse of Indian newes. Or A true and tragicall discourse, shewing the most lamentable miseries, and distressed calamities indured by 67 Englishmen, which were sent for a supply to the planting in Guiana in the yeare. 1605 VVho not finding the saide place, were for want of victuall, left a shore in Saint Lucia, an island of caniballs, or men-eaters in the West-Indyes, vnder the conduct of Captain Sen-Iohns, of all which said number, onely a 11. are supposed to be still liuing, whereof 4. are lately returnd into England. Written by Iohn Nicholl, one of the aforesaid company.</title>
            <author>Nicholl, John, emigrant to Guiana.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110152</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845758</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845758</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176940</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14999)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176940)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 723:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An houre glasse of Indian newes. Or A true and tragicall discourse, shewing the most lamentable miseries, and distressed calamities indured by 67 Englishmen, which were sent for a supply to the planting in Guiana in the yeare. 1605 VVho not finding the saide place, were for want of victuall, left a shore in Saint Lucia, an island of caniballs, or men-eaters in the West-Indyes, vnder the conduct of Captain Sen-Iohns, of all which said number, onely a 11. are supposed to be still liuing, whereof 4. are lately returnd into England. Written by Iohn Nicholl, one of the aforesaid company.</title>
                  <author>Nicholl, John, emigrant to Guiana.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Edward Allde] for Nathaniell Butter, and are to bee solde at his shop neere Saint Austens Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>With a half-title, "An hower-glasse of Indian newes", signed "A" and with a woodcut of a ship.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An houre-glasse of Indian newes.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed "I.C." Variant: dedication signed "Iohn Cooke".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shipwrecks --  Saint Lucia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Saint Lucia --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:1"/>
            <p>An Hower-glaſſe of <hi>Indian</hi> Newes.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of ship</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:2"/>
            <p>AN Houre Glaſse of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Newes.</p>
            <p>OR A true and tragicall diſcourſe, ſhewing the moſt lamentable miſeries, and diſtreſſed Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ties indured by</hi> 67 <hi>Engliſhmen, which were ſent</hi> for a ſupply to the planting in Guiana in the yeare. 1605.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVho not finding the ſaide place, were for want of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               </hi>tuall, left a-ſhore in Saint Lucia, an Iſland of Caniballs, or Men-eaters in the Weſt-Indyes, vnder the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Captain Sen-Iohns, of all which ſaid number; onely a 11. are ſuppoſed to be ſtill liuing whereof 4. are lately returnd into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> Iohn Nicholl, <hi>one of the aforeſaid</hi> Company.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Homo es? humani nila te alienum puta.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for Nathaniell Butter, and are to bee ſolde at his Shop neere Saint <hi>Auſtens</hi> Gate. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:3"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Thomas Smith of London Knight,</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the worſhipfull compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Marchants of London, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Eaſt Indies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fortunate companie of moſt Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, profeſſe themſelues (as it ſeemes in their Dedications) to haue ſuch choiſe of Patrones, that at length there proues but one, which out of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons of choiſe they will make choiſe of. It fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not ſo with mee (right Worſhipfull) who find reaſons weak to induce me, but neceſsitie ſtrong to enforce me to craue your Patronage: Vnleſſe this be a reaſon, that from you alone I can hope for, both that countenance to warrant me, &amp; that courteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, not to diſcountenance mee, that iudgement to finde, and yet that gentlenes to forgiue; being as none of thoſe that are <hi>Intus caeci foris oculati,</hi> ſo neither of thoſe that are wiſe at home, and fooles abroad: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, and delighted to bee acquainted with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine matters, knowing that though they be forraine yet they be humane, &amp; that it is nothing elſe, <hi>Res hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manas negligere:</hi> then <hi>Humanitatem ipſam, naturam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> humanam exucre.</hi> Which if it be a reaſon, it is all, and yet it is ſuch an one as is borrowed from you, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth
<pb facs="tcp:176940:4"/> by you, and dyeth in your diſlike. The caſe then ſtanding (R. Worſhipfull) that I am forced beeing a ſtranger, to betake my ſelfe to ſuch a one, to whoſe knowledge and experience, a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie is but a Cittie, and the whole world a Countrie, &amp; therefore with whom the ſtranger is no ſtranger: I moſt humbly requeſt your Wor. that it be not any way offenſiue to you, which was euery way neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to me. For bee it from anie to imagine, that I ſought heereby to adde anie thing to your Ocean: But who thinkes this, thinkes not a miſſe, that I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the relation of a miſerable and lamentable voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, would ſo much more moue you then manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by how better you apprehend ſuch things then many others.</p>
            <p>Such therefore as it is I haue, and ſuch as I haue, I giue, and in moſte humble and hearty maner, offer to be viewed then, when you giue your ſerious eyes leaue to play. Thus beſeeching God to ſend his continuall, and perpetuall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon you and all yours, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours humble in all dutie:</hi> Iohn Nicholl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, albeit I might be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent how thou cenſure my doings here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, foraſmuch as I haue the thouſand ſtrong of my conſcience to witneſſe with me, that I publiſhed this pamphlet with no worſe intention then with the verie beſt namely to make knowne vnto the world the greatnes and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, miraculouſly ſhewed vnto vs: yet if it would pleaſe thee to think the beſt, thou ſhouldſt adde vnto my ioy, without any detraction from thy ſelfe, nay by ſhewing thy ſelfe to haue <hi>bonum animum,</hi> thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt perſwade me that thou haſt <hi>bonam mentem,</hi> for <hi>bona mens, bonus animus,</hi> a good minde, a good thought. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me intreate thee to be one houre in thy life ſo idle as to abide the running out of this Houre-glaſſe. Many things wee felt which heere are not to be found, by reaſon that the deſperateneſſe of our caſe deliuered them to neglect, and neglect to obliuion. This that is heere is the iuſt account of a perfect memorie, tending not to diſcourage any from attempting the like, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to encourage with the munition of prouidence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Praemonitus, praemunitus,</hi> forewarned, well armed. Thus requeſting you that my wants may bee ſupplied in thy gentleneſſe: adding then ſtrength to thy goodneſſe, when thou meeteſt with my weakeneſſe, I bid the heartily farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine to the beſt of his power:</hi> Iohn Nicholl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:5"/>
            <l>VIS nondum natus, vis viuere mortuus olim?</l>
            <l>Tempora temporibus iunge aliena tuis.</l>
            <l>Vis paruus magnus fieri, vinctuſque ſolutus?</l>
            <l>Tu loca vicinis iunge remota locis.</l>
            <l>Non vita eſt, vitas qua vitat vita alienas:</l>
            <l>Libera mens non eſt ſequitur quae corpus vt vmbra</l>
            <l>Pars vitae, Indorum vita remota, mea eſt,</l>
            <l>Quò mens it libro rapta <hi>(Nichole)</hi> tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <l>DEare bought, far ſought, they ſay wil Ladies pleaſe</l>
            <l>They pleaſ'd, good manners will that meaner be:</l>
            <l>Feare no repulſe, O newes from Indian ſeat!</l>
            <l>For man he is not, is not mannerly.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:5"/>
            <head>A True and Tragicall Diſcourſe, <hi>ſhewing the moſt lamentable miſeries,</hi> and diſtreſſed calamities, indured by 67. Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men, which were ſent for a ſupplie to the planting in <hi>Guiana,</hi> in the yeare 1605.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O make a long and tedious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of that which may be vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in few words, expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, doth rather moue a loathing in the Reader, then any way pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a liking either in reader or hearer: in which reſpect I haue rather deſired briefly to deliuer a plaine truth, which of it ſelfe to the wiſe and diſcreete is euer moſt acceptable, then with filed phraſes, or eloquent termes (which indeede in mee are wanting) to adde any thing more then is moſt true, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to repreſent, or lay open to the view of the worlde, ought more then what my ſelfe with my aſſociates haue had as wofull experience, as euer (in my iudgement) had any creatures liuing vnder the Canopie of Heauen: only thus much I thinke it not impertinent to deliuer, for the better explanation of that which followeth, I make no queſtion, but that the greater ſort of people, which either haue trauailed themſelues, had conuerſation with tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylers, or imployed themſelues to much reading,
<pb facs="tcp:176940:6"/> are not ignorant that in the maine of <hi>America,</hi> in that part thereof which is vulgarly called <hi>The weſt India,</hi> amongſt many other large Teritories &amp; Dominions, is the great and mightie Kingdome of <hi>Guiana,</hi> ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neare about the middle of the ſaide continent, or ſomwhat more ſoutherly, it being neare vnder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial line, the Souther moſt part therof, and extending it ſelfe to about ſome 5. or 6. degrees of North Latitude, being bordered on the South-weſt with <hi>Perue,</hi> on the South with <hi>Amazonis,</hi> on the North with <hi>Mexico,</hi> and on the Eaſt with the Ocean Sea.</p>
            <p>The ſaide Countrey of <hi>Guiana</hi> was firſt diſcouered or made knowne to our Engliſh Nation, as farre as I can learne, about the yeare of our Lord 1594. at the charge and direction principally of Sir <hi>Walter Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh:</hi> the ſame againe ſeconded by himſelfe the yeare following: afterward againe by Captaine <hi>Keymiſh</hi> and oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, at the charges of the ſaid Sir <hi>Walter Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi> it being reputed to bée the chiefeſt place for golde Mines in all the Weſt India: but the proſecution ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being left off for a time, by what occaſion I know not, it ſo happened that in the yeare of our Lord 1602, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Charles Leigh</hi> made a voyage thither, for the diſcouerie thereof, and finding a fit place for habitation, determined to procure the planting of a Colonie there in the Riuer <hi>Wiapica,</hi> which ſaid determination at his returne being put in practiſe, with the furtherance and ſpeciall charge of the worſhipfull Knight Sir <hi>Oliue Leigh,</hi> certaine men were ſent thither, there to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite vnder the conduct of the aforeſaid Captain <hi>Charles Leigh,</hi> who remayned there about a yeare and a halfe, where he with manie of his companie dyed. For a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie vnto which companie, was another companie ſent, in the yeare 1605. at the charges of the ſayde Sir <hi>Oliue Leigh,</hi> and certaine other aduenturers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of which companie my ſelfe was one, all vnder the conduct and
<pb facs="tcp:176940:6"/> leading of Captaine <hi>Sen-Iohns,</hi> who being embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the <hi>Oliue Branch</hi> of Sir <hi>Oliue Leigh,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was captaine and maſter vnder God, captaine <hi>Catlin</hi> and <hi>Arthur Chambers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being thus readie, doe ſet ſaile the twelfth of Aprill one thouſand ſixe hundred and fiue, nothing hapning worth note, till wee came as high as the North Cape, where an Engliſh Barke ouertaking vs, foure of our Gentlemen, by reaſon of their ſickeneſſe were deſirous to returne home againe, ſo that getting their paſſage for <hi>Lisbone,</hi> they tooke their leaue of vs, whoſe names were, Maiſter <hi>Rogers,</hi> Maiſter <hi>Catlin,</hi> Maiſter <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and another whoſe name I doe not now remember. So wee continued our courſe to the <hi>Canaries,</hi> and ſo to Cape <hi>Blancko</hi> in <hi>Barbarie,</hi> and from thence to the Ile of <hi>Mayo:</hi> in which time of our voyage it fell out as often it hapneth in ſuch actions, that our companie being deuided, (as being ſome ſea-men, and the reſt land-men, who are for the moſt part many times of contrarie natures) there was ſome heart-burning and malice one againſt another, which reſted not onely in the common ſort, but rather and moſt chiefly in our captaines, whoſe haughtie mindes not brooking contradiction on either ſide, had like to haue growne to a daungerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, had it not beene appeaſed by the diligent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of ſome other of the companie, whoſe plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſpirites were more addicted to vnitie and peace, then any way liking of ſuch daungerous and indirect courſes, they well fore-knowing that ciuill diſcorde haue beene the ouerthrow of mightie kingdomes, and great common weales, and therefore well might haue béene the vtter ſubuerſion of our ſo weake &amp; ſlenderly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned companie. But all parties being now (as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) to the outward view quieted, we went a ſhore vpon the ſaid Ile of. <hi>Mayo</hi> to take in freſh water and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt, where we found 5. Portugals, which had bin robbed by
<pb facs="tcp:176940:7"/> the French, and there ſet a ſhore, where hauing ſtayed fiue dayes hunting of Goats, and refreſhing of our men, we departed to ſaint <hi>Iago,</hi> where we landed the fiue <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals,</hi> in reward of which kindneſſe of ours, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants tooke thrée of our men, and kept them as priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners while they ſent ſeauen leagues into the Countrey to know the Gouernours pleaſure, and at night ſent them aboord againe, hauing taken certaine commodities from them, which they had to buy ſome of their fruits.</p>
            <p>From thence (hauing weyed our Anchor) with a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie gale we ſailed towardes our deſired place to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Guiana:</hi> but miſſing of our expectation, here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the firſt ſcene of our enſuing miſeries: for whether it was our Maſters want of knowledge that we fell not with the prefixed place, or that the current which our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter alledged to be the reaſon, that ſetting verie ſtrongly to the North-wards, put vs ſo farre ſhort thereof, or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as of all others that is moſt certaine) it pleaſed God in that place at that time, and in ſuch a manner, to let vs feele ſome part of his heauie diſpleaſure, conceyued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs for our times formerly miſpent: ſo as I ſay the ending of our hopes was the beginning of our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: for plying to and againe, wandring as it were in a wilderneſſe of woe, betwixt hope and diſpaire, the time paſſed away &amp; with the time our victuals, the onely hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our health exceedingly waſted: therevpon our allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was greatly ſhortned, &amp; with the ſame &amp; other occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencee our mens minds very much diſtracted, which bred amongſt vs many fearfull &amp; daungerous mutinies. And as one miſerie commeth ſtill in the necke of another, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it with vs: for with our want of victuals, we being neare vnto the Equinoctiall, and the Sun in that part of the Zodiacke which was neare vnto our Zenith, it was ſo exceeding hot, that with the vehemencie thereof many of our men fell maruellous weake, and ſome of them died, namely our Carpenters mate <hi>Iohn Browne,</hi> our
<pb facs="tcp:176940:7"/> Cooke, and <hi>Robert Paine,</hi> and many others were is weake, that they were not able to come aboue the hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. This extremitie cauſed vs (though againſt our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks) to entreate the maſter to bring vs to the neareſt ſhore he could. And ſo hauing beene ſeuenteene wéekes at ſea, in ſtead of our hopefull expectations of attaining to a pleaſant, rich and golden Counteey, and the comfortable companie of our friends and Countrey-men, there as we ſuppoſed then reſident, we were brought to an Iland in the Weſt <hi>India</hi> ſomewhat diſtant from the maine, called <hi>Santa Lucia,</hi> hauing about twelue degrees of North latitude, inhabited onely with a companie of moſt cruell Caniballs and man-eaters, where we had no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner anchored, but the <hi>Carebyes</hi> came in their Peria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes or Boats aboord vs with great ſtore of Tobacco, Plantons, Potatoes, Pines, Sugar Canes, and diuerſe other fruits, with Hens, Chickens, Turtles, &amp; Guauas: for all which we contented and pleaſed them well. Theſe <hi>Carrebyes</hi> at their firſt comming in our ſight, did ſeeme moſt ſtrange and vgly, by reaſon they are all naked, with long blacke haire hanging downe their ſhoulders, their bodies all painted with red, and from their eares to their eyes, they do make three ſtrokes with red, which makes them looke like diuels or Anticke faces, wherein they take a great pride.</p>
            <p>The next morning we went a ſhore with all our weak men, where there was ſixe or ſeauen houſes planted by a pleaſant freſh water Riuer, which Captain <hi>Sen-iohns</hi> bought for a Hatchet of an Indian Captaine called <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie,</hi> who could ſpeake a little Spaniſh, and he told vs he had beene a ſlaue to the Spaniard in the Ile of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta:</hi> ſo he and al his companie went to another towne ſome three myles of.</p>
            <p>Whileſt our ſicke men were a ſhore refreſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, our Maiſter would haue departed, and haue left them to ſhift among the <hi>Carrebyes,</hi> but Captaine <hi>Sen-Iohns,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176940:8"/> and the chiefe of our companie would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto. And ſeeing it was in vaine all of vs for to venter home in the Shippe with that ſmall allowance, wee were willing to come a ſhore, and there to liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it ſhould pleaſe God to ſend ſome meanes to bring vs a way: vpon that condition they ſhould deliuer vnto vs one great peece, and euery man his Muſket and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and halfe the munition in the ſhip, with all our Cheſts and commodities whatſoeuer, which hee would not graunt, before we had ſubſcribed to a certaine Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting which he wrote to excuſe himſelfe at his returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to England: ſo we receyued foure little Barrels of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ten round Bullets for the great Peece, which when wee brought a ſhore did much feare the <hi>Indians,</hi> for they aſked vs if we brought it to kill them. But to pleaſe their humours, wee tolde them it was to kill the Spaniards, and then they came and helped vs a ſhore with her, and with all our Cheſtes, of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</p>
            <p>Now after they had deliuered all things a ſhore out of the Boat, we thought it good to ſtay her, and to kéepe her for our owne vſe, for wee did not know what neede we might haue of ſuch a commoditie afterwarde: ſo wée ſent the ſailers aboord in an Indian Boat, onely three would not goe but would ſtay with vs: ſo we were in all left a ſhore threeſcore and ſeauen in the Iſle of Saint <hi>Lucca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At night when we were all ſitting togither at ſupper about a great fire, which they could well perceue from the ſhip when it was darke: and as it ſhould ſeeme in reuenge of their Boat, before they departed they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to let vs know they were not well pleaſed with the action, they ſhot a great peece at vs with a ſingle Bullet, but as it pleaſed God it fell downe by the ſide of our houſe, and miſſed vs, which if it had come amongeſt vs we ſitting ſo thicke, it could not haue choſen but haue
<pb facs="tcp:176940:8"/> beene the death of many of vs.</p>
            <p>This made Captaine <hi>Sen-Iohns</hi> diſcharge our péece at them, without intent to hurt them, but fairly ouerſhot them: for he might haue ſunke them, and would if they had ſhot once more: then preſently they weyed Anchor and departed.</p>
            <p>The next morning Captaine <hi>Sen-Iohns</hi> went in the Boate, with fifteene more in his companie, to trade with <hi>Anthonio</hi> his father for <hi>Rone</hi> cloath, which he had ſaued at ſea great ſtore: but when we came there, contrarie to our expectation, we found our ſhip there trading with them, who had incenſed the Indians ſore agaynſt vs, telling them that we were had people, and would take all they had from them, and would cut their throats.</p>
            <p>And as we towed alongſt the ſhore, they diſcharged halfe a dozen peece of Ordenance, and a volly of ſmall ſhot at vs, but there great ſhot ouerſhot vs, and light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rockes, and ſcarred the Indians a ſhore mightily, and their ſmall ſhotte light ſhort without harming vs. Their decermination was to driue vs from our Boat, or elſe to haue ſunke her, for their great ſhot came ſo thicke that wee were forced to leape a ſhore into the Woods: then they manned their Periago, and came to take our Boat away, which wee perceyuing entered her againe, and eſcaped all their malice: ſo wee returned home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſafe, and they departed toward Saint <hi>Vincent,</hi> the eighteenth or ninteenth of Auguſt, 1605.</p>
            <p>After the departure of our ſhip we remained in peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able manner amongſt the Indians, dayly trading with them for all manner of victuall, as Plantons, Potatoes, Penas, Papaians, Pumpins, Gallobaſhoes, Pappes, Mammies, Guiauas, with diuerſe other fruits, and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco aboundance, all verie pleaſant to eate. Alſo they brought Turtles, Guanas Hens and Chickens, Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks and Snipes, with ſome Pellicans.</p>
            <p>As for the Turtles, we our ſelues did vſe euery night
<pb facs="tcp:176940:9"/> by courſes to ſend out ſixe to catch them, which is eaſily done, by reaſon that euery night they vſe to come a ſhore, and lay their egs in the ſand, and by the heat of the Sun they are hatched. At their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming out of the water they do make as broad a tract as a Cart with their ſins, by which meanes wee are ledde to the place where they doe ſit, and ſo we turne them on their backes, which being done, they can doe nothing but ſo lie till they bee deade. The meate of them dooth eate like vnto Veale, and I haue ſeene taken out of one of them to the number of ſixe or ſeauen hundred egges, which wee doe frie with the fat or oyle of the Turtle, and alſo with Caſſada wee did make exceeding good White-pots and Puddings, putting the Egges and Oyle into it. Alſo the <hi>Guana</hi> is proportioned like a Serpent, more then an ell long, with foure ſhort feete. In eating it is like a Connie, and hath in his belly to the number of fiue and twentie or thirtie Egges.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Caſſada</hi> is a roote of a tree, whoſe iuce is poyſon: but being ſqueaſſed, the flower doth make an excellent kind of bread, and will kéepe long.</p>
            <p>The Indians did maruaile much at our manner of dreſſing our meate, and they would be familier, and would dine with vs verie often, but by no meanes wee could not make them eate ſalt: for they vſe to eate all their meate ſeaſoned with Ginnie Pepper: their women came verie ſeldome vnto vs, for they are verie iealous ouer them. Once or twice there came ſome wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with them, vnto whome wee gaue ſhirts to couer their nakedneſſe, whereof they ſeemed proud: Their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient women are verie vgly, by reaſon of their ſide breaſtes, which dooth lie like emptie bagges: but thoſe which haue not giuen ſucke, are well proportioned and proper.</p>
            <p>Alſo we had a Net, with the which wee would get at one draught as many fiſh of diuerſe ſorts, as would
<pb facs="tcp:176940:9"/> ſerue all our companie a day.</p>
            <p>A little before our arriuall, three Spaniſh ſhips were caſt away, and much of the goodes theſe Indians had ſaued with their Boats, and hid it in the Woods, they had ſo much Roan cloath, that all their Periagoes had ſayles thereof. They alſo had great ſtore of ſtuffe, Sirge, and Spaniſh woollen cloath, cloakes and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell: inſomuch that if we had had a Barke of fortie tuns burthen, wee could haue loaden her home with ſuch commodities as would haue made a ſauing voyage. All which we could haue bought for hatchets, kniues, beads, fiſh-hookes, and thimbles, with other trifles.</p>
            <p>Thus for the ſpace of fiue or ſixe Weekes, wee went not much abroade, but cut downe the Woods about our houſes euerie day, and mounted our great Peece vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on broade Tables, which wee our ſelues had ſawne, leaſt the <hi>Carrebyes</hi> ſhould at any time aſſault vs.</p>
            <p>Soone after this, there came onother Captaine from Saint <hi>Vincent,</hi> called <hi>Augraumart,</hi> which was brother to <hi>Anthonio,</hi> who was offended with him for ſelling the houſes vnto vs: for the which cauſe <hi>Anthonio</hi> bid vs kill him, and tolde vs hee purpoſed to bring twelue Periagoes loaden with <hi>Carrebyes</hi> to kill vs, but wee found this <hi>Augraumart</hi> verie kinde vnto vs, and was willing to doe, or tell vs any thing wee deſired him, for he taught vs to make a Grater, which he made of ſmall ſharpe flint ſtones beaten into a broade boord to grate our <hi>Caſſada</hi> on, whereof we made our breade, and hee tolde vs, that <hi>Anthonio</hi> would cut our throates, and therefore bid vs kill him. This made vs doubtfull which to truſt to.</p>
            <p>We had certaine Articles drawne, which were to bée obſerued, wherein Captaine <hi>Nicholas Sen-Iohns</hi> was Captaine: his brother <hi>Alexander</hi> Lieutenant, <hi>Miles Pet,</hi> and <hi>Philip Glaſcock</hi> were commaunders for the appoynting of our Watch: <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> was our
<pb facs="tcp:176940:10"/> interpreter for the Spaniſh tongue, and was to buy and bargaine with the Indians for all the companie, both for commodities and victuals, Maiſter <hi>Garret,</hi> Maſter <hi>Tench, Francis Brace,</hi> and my ſelfe, were appointed to order the domeſticall matters.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Carebie</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies in their language, A valiant man.</note>All the occaſions y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we made whereby the <hi>Carrebyes</hi> ſhould fall out with vs, was that one of our companie did ſell a ſworde vnto Captaine <hi>Anthonio,</hi> which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the Articles wee had ſet downe, for none was (vpon paine of ſeuere puniſhment) to ſel either Sworde, Dagger, or Hedge-bill: which when we knew, <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sen-Iohns</hi> with a dozen more went to his houſe, and found him in his bed, which they call an <hi>Hamaco,</hi> with a little fire vnder him becauſe hs was not well, and the Sword ſtanding by him, which yong <hi>Sen-Iohns</hi> tooke and brought forth to vs. This droue him into a great rage againſt vs, for neuer after that would he be familiar with vs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Carrebyes</hi> did weare for an ornament vpon the ſmall of their naked aimes a foure-ſquare plate, which maiſter <hi>Browne</hi> a Gold-finer told Captaine <hi>Sen-Iohns</hi> had three partes of it Golde, who aſked the <hi>Carrebyes</hi> where they got it? who preſently pointed vs to a great Mountaine on the North-weſt part of the Iſland, whoſe toppe we might ſee from the place where wee dwelt: but <hi>Anthonio</hi> ſaide there was none. Theſe contrarie tales made vs ſuſpect ſome villanie, and that it was but a pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to drawe ſome of our companie thither, whereby they might the better deale with vs: for at home they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt not attempt any thing againſt vs, both for feare of our great Peece, and alſo wee would not ſuffer them to bring their bowes and arrowes within our Centi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell. Yet our Captaine would not bee content till wee conſented that hee ſhould goe to the Mountaine, and tooke with him all ſortes of commodities to bargaine with the Indians for Cloath, and he tooke old <hi>Browne</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176940:10"/> the Gold-finer, and his ſonne <hi>George Browne, Iohn Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> Maiſter <hi>Looking,</hi> the three ſailers, whoſe names were, <hi>Iohn Fleming, Thomas Butler, Owen</hi> a Welch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Iames Garret,</hi> &amp; one <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> two Grocers, and one Maiſter <hi>Euans,</hi> with diuerſe more, to the number of ſixtéene.</p>
            <p>And vpon A Monday they all imbarked in the Boat taking eight dayes victuall with them, promiſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn betwixt that and the next Monday, leauing his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Miles Pet, Philip Glaſcock,</hi> M. <hi>Garret,</hi> M. <hi>Tench,</hi> and my ſelfe, to rule at home. Vpon Tueſday &amp; Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the Indians did not come vnto vs with victuals as they had wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which made vs after ſuſpect that they were at the ſlaughter of our men at the Mount: &amp; vpon Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday, my ſelfe with 3. more went to <hi>Anthonios</hi> houſe, where we found a great number of women, but not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing halfe a ſcore men, making great preparation of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals: ſome baking of Caſſada, others roaſting and boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of great fiſhes and Turtles. I offred to buy ſome of them, but they refuſed and would not, neither would they looke of any commoditie we had, which made vs much maruell: for before that time they neuer denied vs: ſo we departed, &amp; by the way we light of a narrow path where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we trauelled a little, and all along the way did growe aboundance of Guiaua trees, whoſe fruit is as big as an Apple, and verie pleaſant to eate: the greene ones are wholeſome for the bloodie flixe.</p>
            <p>Wee had not trauayled a Mile, but wee entered downe by a Thicket into a moſt pleaſant Garden of Potatoes, which droue vs into greate admiration to beholde the manner of it, for it was made round like a Bower, encompaſſed with a greene Banke, ſo equally, that made vs thinke ſome Chriſtians had made it for a ſtrength to ſaue them from the Indians: and vppon the toppe thereof did growe a companie of the moſte
<pb facs="tcp:176940:11"/> talleſt Trées that euer I behelde, which did naturally growe ſo neere one to another, and ſo thicke from the roote to the toppe, that wee could not perceyue the ſkie through them. But following the path, wee percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it to paſſe through a narrow cut in the banke, where wee traueyled two or three miles further, paſſing through many goodly Gardens, wherein was aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Caſſada, Potatoes, Tobacco, Cotten-wool-trees, and Guiaua trees, in diuerſe places as wee tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled wee did maruaile to ſee the huge and great trées that were there: for moſt of them were fiue or ſixe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoms about, and fearing that wee ſhoulde bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nighted, wee returned the ſame way againe, with as much greene Tobacco, Potatoes, and Caſſada, as wee could carrie, which did much content our men at home: for the Indians had not brought any victuals in three dayes before.</p>
            <p>At night ſixe of our men went to ſeeke for Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and founde two verie great ones, but could not bring them home. For when they had turned them on their backes, it beganne to raine, thunder, and lighten ſo extreamly, that they had much a doe to get home themſelues, and ſo it continued all night, with the moſte horribleſt thunder-claps that euer I heard, with lightning and raine as light as day, which cauſed vs to awake, and after prayers to fit all night by greate Fiers, drinking of Tobacc, with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie myrth amongeſt our ſelues, little fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the daunger that befell to vs the next day.</p>
            <p>Earely the next Morning, wee went to bring home our Turtles, and there wee founde a great number of <hi>Carrebyes</hi> on the ſhore, and three or foure Boates by them, roaſting of lande Crabbes, for what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they were ſo gathered together wee know not, but leaſt we ſhould ſuſpect them of any bad intent towardes
<pb facs="tcp:176940:11"/> vs, they willed vs to eate with them, and brought home our Turtles to our houſes.</p>
            <p>All that fore-noone wee kept good watch, for there was verie many which came both by Sea and land. and <hi>Augraumart</hi> and his father came with a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Indians, and brought in his hande a quarter of a Turtle, and a hundred Egges, and gaue them to young <hi>Sen-Iohns,</hi> and tolde him, that if hee would goe to his Brother <hi>Anthonius</hi> houſe, hee ſhould haue greate ſtore of victualls, and that hee ſhould ſee his wife, and the more to perſwade vs to goe, hee promiſed that wee ſhould haue Hamacas for to ſleepe in, which is the beds they vſe.</p>
            <p>Their Women dooth make them of Cotten that growes naturallye on the Trees, wereof they haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance. Wee manye times made ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te vnto them for their Hamacas, becauſe they would bee a meanes to ſaue vs from the Stings of curtaine. Flor called a Muſketo, the which would ſo torment vs with their pay loued ſtings, and cauſe vs to ſwell as though we had the Leproſie, for they would ſting through three payr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Stockings, but they were not willing till now on the ſuddaine that wee ſhould haue any. And becauſe they were ſo kinde to vs, wee tooke them all into our houſes, and were verie merrye and pleaſant with them, and gaue them <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> which they delighted much in.</p>
            <p>But Maiſter <hi>Tench</hi> (who had wont to bee a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous corrector of vs in our merr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments) did ſhow himſelfe ſo extraordinarie pleaſant, that hee fell a ſinging of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with the <hi>Carrebyes,</hi> and cauſed them in drinke ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſes of <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> and water.</p>
            <p>If wee had beene determined to haue kild them, wee might haue done it at that time with ſmall danger, wee had a hundreth and aboue of them within out hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes without eyther dowe or Arrowes. And when ſome
<pb facs="tcp:176940:12"/> of our companie, made ſuch a motion as to put them to the Sworde (for ſome of vs was halfe and more iealous of them, that they had done ſome miſchiefe to our cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, by reaſon one of our companie did ſay, that hee heard an Indian ſay, that the Captaine of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh had his hande cutte off at the Mount) but this was not regarded, but was imputed that hee had miſconſtrued the <hi>Carrobyes</hi> language. Maiſter <hi>Tench</hi> was agaynſt it, ſaying: God woulde not bee pleaſed with ſuch a bloudie Act, agaynſt ſuch harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe people, and therefore willed vs not to doe it without they gaue the firſt occaſion, wherein hee wronged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and vs all, in ſeeking to ſaue the liues of them, who within three houres after moſt cruellye mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered him.</p>
            <p>Before Dinner they all departed, but <hi>Augrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mart</hi> and his father, who dined with vs. And pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after dinner, eighteene was choſen to goe to <hi>Anthonios</hi> houſe with <hi>Augraumart</hi> and his father, who had neither bowe nor arrow: onely his father had a Braſell ſworde.</p>
            <p>This they did leaſt wee ſhoulde ſuſpect their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie. But wee not fearing anie treaſon, becauſe wee had beene often times well vſed there before, went on boldly,</p>
            <p>And ſome of our companie thought that the verie fight of our Peeces was ſufficient to terrifie them, for attempting any villany againſt vs. And therfore did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egarde either to charge them, or to light our match.</p>
            <p>In this careleſſe and ſecure manner wee trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led through a little necke of land which runnes farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea, and then wee entered vpon the ſand, which was ſo extreame hote with the reflexion of the Sunne that wee were not able to trauaile apace, being loaden with our Peeces.</p>
            <p>But Maiſter <hi>Alexander</hi> had put off his Doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let,
<pb facs="tcp:176940:12"/> and gaue his Boy his Peece, &amp; went ieſting &amp; play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arme in arme with the two <hi>Carrebyes</hi> a good ſpace before vs, vntil wee came to a point of Land a quarter of a mile from <hi>Anthonios</hi> houſe, and then hee called vs to come forward, but hee beeing light and coole, did keepe a greate way before vs ſtill. And when hee leaſt ſuſpected daunger, <hi>Augraum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> made as though hee would imbrace him, And ſuddenlye claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping holde with one hand on his Rapyer, and the other on his Dagger, and his Father with a great Bruſſell Sword, ſtrooke him downe before we could come at him, but he recouered againe.</p>
            <p>Then came the Arrowes ſo thicke out of the wood, that we could not get our match in the Cocke for pulling the Arrowes out of our bodyes: ſo amongſt vs all was but fiue or ſixe peeces diſcharged, which when the Indians ſaw giue fire, they did fall flat on the ground, ſhouting and crying with a moſte helliſh noyſe, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vs by our names when they hit vs.</p>
            <p>Then wee retyred backe to a poynt of land, thinking there to haue fitted our peeces, and to haue giuen them a volley of ſhot, But there came another Ambuſh on our backes, and round about vs, inſomuch that wee were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to forſake our peeces, and betake vs to our ſwords, which did much incourage them, for when they ſee wee could not hurt them with our peeces, they would come ſo neere vs, as though they purpoſed to make choyce in what place to hit vs, of ſome they ſhot in the faces, others through the Shoulders, and of others, they would naile their feete and the ground together.</p>
            <p>Maiſter <hi>Budge</hi> and <hi>Robert Shaw</hi> ranne into the ſea, and there were both drowned and kild with Arrowes, Maiſter <hi>Tench</hi> had a little Bucklet, with the which bee did ſaue himſelfe a long time, but at the laſt an Arrowe paſſed through both his legges, that hee could not goe,
<pb facs="tcp:176940:13"/> and ſtooping to pull it out, they kild him, and if anye of vs offered to runne at one or two of them, they would runne away, and of a ſuddaine twentie or thirtie would incloſe vs, and ſtill ſhoote Arrowes in them til they were downe, and then would they with a great Braſſell ſword beate them to death, and after would rifle them: Maiſter <hi>Kettleby</hi> did behaue himſelfe verie gallantlye, for hee did not reſpect what arrowes hee receiued in his bodye, ſo hee could but reach one ſtroke at a <hi>Carrebye,</hi> but they were too nimble for vs in regard they were naked.</p>
            <p>Yet neuertheleſſe, wee runne through them all, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that if wee had eſcaped that ambuſh, there had béen no more to trouble vs, but as I was a pulling Arrowes out of his bodye, to the number of twentie at the leaſt, there came the third ambuſh out of the woodes from whence came an Arrowe and hit him in the Breaſt, which hee perceiued would bee his death, for hee could not ſtand but as I hold him, but I was forced to let him goe, and ſhift to ſaue my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Then I ouer tooke young <hi>Sen-Iohns</hi> his bodye almoſt full of Arrowes, of which I pulled out a number, But what for the bloud that runne from him, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame heate hee was in by his running, hee was not able to ouertake the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of our companye that was before.</p>
            <p>And ſtill the <hi>Carrebyes</hi> did gather ground vppon vs, and the Arrowes came thicke on euerie ſide.</p>
            <p>Then hee willed mee to intreate them ſtay, and when I had ouertaken one, I cauſed him to ſtay, which hee was vnwilling to doe, for hee tolde mee his Sword would not come foorth of the Scabberd, ſo I tooke hold of the Hilts, and betwixt vs both pulled it out, but before wee had made an ende, theſe cruell and bloodye <hi>Carre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes</hi> had encompaſſed yong <hi>Sen-Iohns</hi> yet (to my griefe) I did ſtand and beholde his ende, who before hee fell
<pb facs="tcp:176940:13"/> did make them run like ſo many Curres from a Lyon: for looke which way hee ran, they all fled before him: his body was ſo loaden with Arrowes, that he fell to the ground: and vpon one hand and knees, hee did keepe them from him with his Swoord, ſo much hee ſcorned ſo baſely to dye at their handes.</p>
            <p>We two were then the onely markes they aymed at: for hauing rifled young <hi>Seniohus,</hi> they purſued vs very hotly, which cauſed vs make haſte to foure of our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, who were entred into a narrow path, which lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth through the woods, from the ſandes to the Houſes where wee dwelt: but there was in the path an other Ambuſh, which droue them backe to the ſandes againe: and when they ſaw vs ſo hardly chaſed, they entred the path with vs againe.</p>
            <p>The one ſide of the path was a high Mountayne, the other went downe a low Valley. The firſt foure tooke vp the Mountayn, by which meanes, they were a fayre marke for them to hitte, who dropped downe one after another.</p>
            <p>All this time, neyther <hi>Harry</hi> which was M. <hi>Stokeleys</hi> man (a Marchant now in <hi>Bucklersbery</hi>) nor my ſelfe was ſhot: but as we thought deſperatly to run through them in the narrowe path, there came an Arrowe and pearced quite through his head, of the which he fell ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and I ran to lift him vp, but he was dead without ſpeaking one word to mee at all.</p>
            <p>Then came there two Arrowes and hitte mee in the back, the one directly againſt my hart, the other through my ſhoulder blade: ſo (with my ſwoord in my hande) I ran vpon them deſperatly, thinking (before I had died) to haue ben the death of ſome of them. And in my run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I ſaw Captaine <hi>Anthony,</hi> with an Arrow in his Bow drawne againſt me, who ſtood vntill I came very néere him (for he purpoſes to haue ſped mée with that
<pb facs="tcp:176940:14"/> ſhot) which when I ſée come. I thought to put it by with my ſwoord, but it light on my hand, &amp; paſſed thorow the handle of my ſword, and nayled both together: but I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued running at him ſtill; and before he could nocke an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, I made him and all the reſt turne their backs, and run into the ſands againe: which oportunity when I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyed, I leapt into the wood, downe to the valley, where I found a great Lake: And hearing them, with great ſhowts and cry, which they vſe in ſigne of tryumph and victory, purſue mee ſtill, I leapt into the Lake, with my ſword nayled to my hand, and two arrowes in my backe, and by the helpe of God ſwamme ouer, but with much adoo: for the further ſide was ſhallow water, but I wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in mud vp to the waſte, which had almoſt ſpent me.</p>
            <p>Now when I was ouer, I conuayd my ſelfe into the thickeſt parts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wood, making all the haſte I could, to giue my fellowes, which were at home, warning, leſt the <hi>Indians</hi> ſhould ſet on them vnawares: and in my going, I came into a path, and ſought for a great trée, to ſée, if by the ayme of the Iland, I could perceyue which way our houſes ſtood. Then ſuddenly I heard a great noyſe, which made me ſtand behind a tree, and there I ſaw two or three <hi>Indians</hi> goe by me, which I imagined were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſet on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at home: but it pleaſed God I got home, &amp; gaue warning before their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming: ſo <hi>Miles Pet</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our great Peece, and al our men were in redines for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. Then preſently, they all came in ſight vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſands, whome we ſent away (by ſhooting of our great Peece) &amp; came no more in 3. daies: in which time, we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified our ſelues with our Cheſts: And vpon Munday morning (before wee had made an end of praier) there came to the number of 13. or 14. C. <hi>Indians</hi> (both by ſea and land,) &amp; there beſet vs round, making a noyſe with their Hornes, and made moſt horrible cryes, which they no vſe, the more to terryfle their enemies: and we did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb facs="tcp:176940:14"/> them agayne with the lyke cryes, deuyding our ſelues into 4 parts, according as we had made our Forts of our Cheſts, placing fiue in euery Forte, and thrée to the great Péece, where <hi>Miles Pett,</hi> my ſelfe and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other was. Then they ſhot their Arrowes among vs as thicke as hayle, and leſt they ſhould follow in vpon vs and make vſe of thoſe Arrowes agayne, we gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them all together, &amp; made great fires with them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their faces, and many times they purpoſed to ruſh in vpon vs by multitudes, &amp; to haue beaten vs downe with their Brazell Swoordes: But our great Peece was ſo mounted, that very readyly we could turne it which way we pleaſed, and looke which way their greateſt company went, we let her flye amongſt them. So perceiuing that they could not preuaile againſt vs, they put Cotten wooll vpon the end of their Arrowes, and put fire on them and ſhot at our Houſes which were made on long Canes or Réedes, and ſuddenly tooke fire by reaſon of the heat of the day, &amp; burned downe to the ground, faſtning on our Cheſts which were our Forts, and burned all downe to the ground, the extreme heat of the flame did make our men forſake their Forts, and retyre behinde the great Péece, to the Sea-ſide, which incouraged the <hi>Carrabies</hi> mightily. M. <hi>William Kettleby</hi> lay cloſe vnſéene of the <hi>Indians</hi> vpon the ſand, and with a long Peece hee would reach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 12. ſcore paces, &amp; galled them much: otherwiſe, they would haue come on the backes of vs by Sea, but he ſhot their Boats thorow and thorow, and ſcard them for entring that way. Now, when al our men were fled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the great Peece, onely <hi>Philip Glaſcocke</hi> &amp; <hi>Richard Garrat</hi> ſtood behinde the ſmoke, and marked where they purpoſed to enter, &amp; eche of them diſcharged halfe a ſcore times at them: At laſt, <hi>Philip Glaſcocke</hi> receiued an Arrowe in his head, and <hi>Richard Garrat</hi> one in his Breſt, and two in his backe. And when the
<pb facs="tcp:176940:15"/> 
               <hi>Indians</hi> ſaw that all were fled but them two, they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to enter through the ſmoake vpon vs: but in the entring, hée gaue a warning to <hi>Miles Pett</hi> to turne the Peece againſt the ſmoake: which preſently we did, and let flye amongſt them and droue them all backe, with moſt lamentable ſkrikes and cryes: no doubt but that ſhot was the death of many of them: for ſhe was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with ſtones. Then they blew their great Hornes, and all rety<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed backe to their Boates, without ſhooting one Arrowe at vs.</p>
            <p>After that our houſe was burned and all our Cheſts, which before were our Fort, we fortified our ſelues with the remnants of the ſtakes, and thatch which we ſaued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burning, ſetting it in the ground ſlepewiſe, couering it with Sand &amp; Earth, which ſaued vs euer after from their Arrowes.</p>
            <p>In all theſe extreme dangers and imminent Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which all this while we endured, let the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader iudge in what a perplexed ſtate we were plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſéeing ſtill one miſery to follow another, and each miſery farre exceeding the former: As firſt, our danger at Sea to be famiſhed: then a comfortleſſe remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Famiſhment, to be lett in a farre remote and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne place, amongſt a cruell, barbarous and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane people, without hope of euer hauing any meanes to recouer the ſight of our natiue and deare countrey and friends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then the loſſe of our Captaine (and others) which before (in all extremity) was ſtill ſome comfort vnto vs: And now (laſtly) theſe lamentable ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems of the maſſacre of our fellowes and friends, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſéeing as in a Glaſſe, the vtter ruine and Butcherly murthering of our owne ſelues, being we made moſt aſſured accompt to drinke of the ſame Cuppe: But this was the leaſt of our feares, and not the greateſt of our miſeries: For being now for a time rid of our bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty
<pb facs="tcp:176940:15"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Which departed in their Peria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos.</note> enemies, our prouiſion of victuals being al wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, ſpent and ſpoyled, and hauing no meanes to get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, it would haue mooued the heart of the cruelleſt Tirant in the world to compaſſion. But in the midſt of all this vnendurable miſery, it pleaſed God (contrary to our expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in ſome ſort) to relieue vs euen by our enemyes: For when all the reſt were out of ſight, one <hi>Periago</hi> returned very well prouided of victual, and thrée or foure came on land, with as much as they were able to carry of <hi>Caſſada, Potatos</hi> &amp; <hi>Plantons,</hi> and cryed vnto vs to exchange with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, firſt holding vp their Bowes, and after laying them on the ground againe in ſigne of peace: which we perceiuing, ſent out three likewiſe to bargain without weapons, carrying Kniues, Beades and other trifles: Which being done, they departed, and we returned, giuing prayſe to God (thus miraculouſly) for to feede vs, for wée had no meanes of our ſelues to get any.</p>
            <p>Then, the Nette (with the which we had wont get aſmuch fiſh of all ſorts as would ſuffiſe vs all for a day) the <hi>Indians</hi> tooke from vs.</p>
            <p>Thus for the ſpace of 6. or 7. dayes, euery day figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the ſpace of thrée or foure houres, and then our victuall began to faile againe, which cauſed vs to hold out a Flag of truce: which the <hi>Indians</hi> perceiuing, came in peaceable maner vnto vs, Then one <hi>Francis Brace</hi> (by meane of his French tongue) made them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that our deſire was to giue them all that wee had, if they would let vs haue a <hi>Periago</hi> to carry vs away, which one Captain <hi>Antonio</hi> willingly conſented vnto, and the next day after brought her, drawing her aſhore within the compaſſe of our Fortes, we giuing them, of Hatchets, Kniues and Beads vntyll they were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And to pleaſe them the more, we gaue them euery one a Shouell or a Spade, and ſo they departed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:16"/>
            <p>And then wee went all to worke, ſome to make the Sayle, which wee made of very good <hi>Roane</hi>-cloath, and ſome to make the Maſt: and euery one did labour all that he could, to bee ready againſt night: for <hi>Antonio</hi> told vs, that his Brother <hi>Angrauemart</hi> would come the next day from S. <hi>Vincent</hi> with twelue <hi>Perriagos,</hi> all laden with men and Arrowes: whoſe words we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way found true, for he could not diſſemble.</p>
            <p>And wee concluded, rather then wee would ſtay and dye ſo miſerably at the <hi>Carrabies</hi> hands, who thirſted for nothing but to eate our fleſh, and drinke our blood, as they had done with many other of our fellowes, wee promiſed vnto the LORD (who had all this tyme fought for vs,) to betake our ſelues vnto his mercy, and doubted not but that hee would guide vs ſafely to ſome Chriſtian Harbour.</p>
            <p>And vpon the xxvi. of September. 1605. at one a clocke after midnight, we embarqued all xix. in that little Veſſell or Boate which the <hi>Indians</hi> had made all of one trée, ſhee was not ſo broade as a Wherry, but it was almoſt as long agayne: Our Roapes for our Sayle were our Garters, and our Yard, a Lance: Shée had a little Rother or Helme, but not one of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had ſkyll howe to vſe it, neyther had wee Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to direct vs, but ſayling by the Sunne in the day, and by the Starres in the night, kéeping al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes betwixt South-weſt and Weſt: for wee ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, the maine Land of the Weſt-Indies lay ſo.</p>
            <p>The Victuals that wee had, were not ſufficïent to ſerue that company three dayes: for we had not aboue twentie Biſkets, three <hi>Caſſada</hi> Cakes, a doſen <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons,</hi> and ſome thirty <hi>Potatos:</hi> and of Water, ſome foure or fiue Gallons, &amp; a little Barrell halfe full of Rice, which Maſter <hi>Garrard</hi> had giuen him to ſerue in the Country of <hi>Guyana,</hi> if we had gotten thyther.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:16"/>
            <p>And as it pleaſed the Lord, hee had ſaued it, vntill this our great neceſſitie for the preſeruation of our liues: for all our other victuall was gone in two dayes, our water in three daies, &amp; then <hi>Richard Garrard</hi> gaue to euery two of vs a Porindiſh of his Rice twice a day, which wee waſhed in ſalt water &amp; ſo eate it rawt. Thus wee continued at Sea, ſeeking for land for the ſpace of tenne dayes, where wee indured one great tempeſt, although to our great perill, looking alwayes when wee ſhould bee ſwallowed vp in the huge waues, the ſtorme continewing for the ſpace of foure and twentie houres, both boyſterous for winde and rayne (for all the Sea was in a white foome) which was vnto vs in the midſt of our danger, a great comfort: for wee ſaued the rayne water and druncke it gladly, thanking God for that good refreſhing: who likewiſe ſent the very fowles of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ayre to léede vs, for they being wery of their flight, would reſt them on the ſide of our boate, ſo that wee tooke them and dried them in the Sunne, with a little Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder and eate them. Our boate was ſo neere the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that euery waue came ouer her reddie to ſinke her, but that foure of vs did nothing but laue it out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by courſes. To ſpeake of the miſery we indured there, it is vnpoſſible; for I cannot expreſſe it.</p>
            <p>Vpon the tenth day after our comming foorth of S. <hi>Lucea,</hi> beyng the fifth of October, one <hi>Thomas Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane</hi> died, not being able to liue of that ſmall allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And at twelue a clocke at noone wee threwe him ouer-boord: and within an houre after, it pleaſed God to glad vs with a ioyfull ſight of the land: then wee boiſted vp our ſayle, fell to rowe with all the force wee could, making to the néereſt place, imagining all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers were paſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:17"/>
            <p>But the winde béeing calme, we were benighted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wée could come at it, and ſo wanting the light of the day, wee were vpon the Rockes before wee were aware: and by reaſon that the breach of the waue was ſo great and violent, we could not holde her off, but (forceably) ranne againſt the Rockes, and there ſplit our Boate to the very middeſt, and all our men tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out, I onely holding the Helme, thinking the next Waue would heaue her ouer the Rockes, not knowing her to bée ſplit.</p>
            <p>But the Breach was ſo great, that it turned mée vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, putting mee in great danger to bee grated to pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with her weyght aboue mee againſt the great Rockes: And at the laſt, wee all recouered our ſelues, ſome ſitting vpon great Rockes, others on the rootes of great Trées, thynking there to ſaue our ſelues tyll the morning: And I finding a long Poale which fell out of our Beate, tooke it and aſked if any would ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the ſhoare with mee: which <hi>Francis Brace</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing, tooke the other-ende: So we two waded to the Land, and then the reſt all followed, and ſome brought Perrywinckles in their handes, and broke them out of the ſhelles and did eate them rawe: then euery one cryed out for freſh Water. So <hi>William Pickes</hi> and my ſelfe went to ſéeke for water: but we had not gone halfe an houre, but wee came to our Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes agayne, without finding of any Water to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs withall. So, the place where we landed, proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be a broken Iſland incompaſſed with the Sea, about a league from the Mayne.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as it was Day, wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igged pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es in the ground for freſh water, but could finde none that was to bee drunke: ſome went to the Boate to ſaue ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modyties, as were left vndriuen away with the Sea: Others found Perrywinckles on the Rockes, which
<pb facs="tcp:176940:17"/> was all the victuall wee had to eate: but our ſtomacks were ſo weake, we could not eate aboue two or thrée a day. Thus not knowing what courſe to take to ſaue our liues from famine, one <hi>Myles Pet, William Pickes,</hi> and my ſelfe went and haled the Boat out of the rockes to the ſhore, which was ſplit to the very midſt, and ſo far with our ſwords we cut off, &amp; put in a head in the midſt, and faſtned it with our Daggers, Kniues, and Bodkins, ſtopping all the leakes with our ſhirtes.</p>
            <p>So fiue of our company ventered in her to the maine land, their names were <hi>Myles Pett, William Kettlebie, William Pickes, Francis Brace,</hi> and <hi>William Butcher,</hi> leauing <hi>Richard Garrard, Philip Glaſcocke, Iohn Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and my ſelfe with the reſt in this hungry and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Iſland. And at laſt it pleaſed God to bring them to the maine land: they haled their Boate alongſt the ſhore, croſſing many great riuers, wherin they were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued by diuers deuouring Serpents of the Sea, as the <hi>Alligortos,</hi> who are of ſuch force, that they will pull a horſe vnder water and deuour him, and will trauell more then two leagues from the water to ſéeke their prayes: And alſo that greedy <hi>Sharke,</hi> who hath thrée rankes of téeth ſet like a ſaw, and will bite off a mans thigh at one ſnatch.</p>
            <p>Yet God preſerued them miraculouſly: And when they were like to giue ouer trauelling, being in deſpaire for euer to find any <hi>Spaniards</hi> for to ſuccour them with foode, God pittying their eſtates, guided them to a place where they found a great Earthen pot full of wheat flower, which they boyled with freſh water,<note place="margin">A pot of flower ſet in a Caue by ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian.</note> and ſatiſfied their hungry appetites with thankes to God for the ſame. And within two dayes after, they met with thrée <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and with halfe a dozen <hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Negros,</hi> trauelling from <hi>Carraccas</hi> to <hi>Coro,</hi> driuing horſes and Mules loaden with Marchandize.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:18"/>
            <p>Who ſéeing their weakeneſſe for want of victual, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loaded their beaſts to feed on the graſſe, whileſt they fed our hungry men with plentie of their good cheare, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them great courteſie, ſuffering them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide, &amp; went themſelues afoote two or thrée dayes, till they came to a towne of ciuill <hi>Indians,</hi> called <hi>Tocoya,</hi> where they ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to refreſh them.</p>
            <p>And there they let the <hi>Spaniards</hi> know in what mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable caſe they left vs in a deſolate Iſland, where wee indured the greateſt miſery that euer men did and liue: for wee continued fiftéene dayes, hauing no kinde of meat but Periwinckles or Whelkes, Tobacco, &amp; Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, which did nothing at all nouriſh vs: yet it tooke away the deſire of hunger, and ſaued vs from eating one another.</p>
            <p>In that fiftéene dayes fiue of our companie pined to death for hunger: Their names were <hi>Iohn Perkins, Edward Greene, Ierome Swaſh, Thomas Stubs,</hi> and an olde man called <hi>Iohn.</hi> Tobacco was the chiefe food I found to do me good, and did preſerue my lyfe, and thoſe which could take it downe, did kéepe ſtrongeſt, but thoſe which could not take it at all, died firſt.</p>
            <p>By noting one or two of our men to die, wee knewe when any of vs drewe neere our death, which was, firſt they would ſwell very bigge, and after, fall to the very bones, and then wanting natural ſtrength in their backs to hold vp their heades, it would fall downe and droupe in there boſomes, and within twelue houres after they would die.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">At the 15. daies end.</note>
               <hi>Francis Brace,</hi> hauing more ſtrength then the reſt, guided the three <hi>Spaniards</hi> to the Iſland where we were, wee little expecting it, for wee thought they had béene kilde, eyther by wild beaſtes or Saluages, and wee had giuen ouer looking for comfort, but euery one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly deſiring God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> himſelfe might not be the laſt man
<pb facs="tcp:176940:18"/> of dying: which conceit was worſe then death it ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. But his returne did adde much comfort vnto vs in that diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe: for they brought vs victuall, which when wee had eate had almoſt kild vs, by reaſon of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſtomackes, beyng ſo farre ſpent, that wee could not diſgeſt it, although we did eate it very ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly.</p>
            <p>The next day the <hi>Spaniards</hi> carried vs to the maine land, where wee had horſes brought vs, and the goods we had, they tooke it all for the King of Spaines vſe, and then they conuaied vs to <hi>Tocoya,</hi> where we which were weake remained for fiftéene daies, and thoſe which were ſtrong went to <hi>Coro,</hi> fiftie leagues from <hi>Tocoya.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the 15. daies end, one of the three <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Signior Carow Vallo,</hi> came for vs with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who ſhewed himſelfe as carefull to vs, as if wee had béene his owne Countrymen and friends, &amp; in 5. daies brought vs to <hi>Coro</hi> to our fellowes, where wee were brought before the Gouernour, and by a Flemming which could ſpeake a little Engliſh, which had been pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner there ſixteene yeres, we were examined of the cauſe of our comming on that coaſt, who excuſed vs very well, for he knew, that if we confeſſed whither wee were deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to goe meaning <hi>Guiana,</hi> they would eyther haue put vs to death, or condemned vs to the Gallies to rowe. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e told them, that wee neuer purpoſed to come into the Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> but that we were by miſfortune and tempeſt driuen on that coaſt, and told them of all the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and dangers we had indured and eſcaped, which droue them into great admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying we were deuils and not men. And the Fleming told vs, the fathers of their churches ſaid, that if we had béene good Chriſtians, we deſerued to be canonized for Saints: but in regard we were <hi>Lutherans,</hi> it was more by the deuils meanes, then by the prouidence of God wee eſcaped thoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:19"/>
            <p>So all the chiefe of the Towne being there, euery man was deſirous to take one of vs, who did not vſe vs like pryſoners, but were as carefull of vs as of their owne children, not ſuffering vs to want any thing that was neceſſary for the procuring of our health.</p>
            <p>My ſelfe beyng extreme ſicke of the Callienturo, one Captain <hi>Peroſo,</hi> who married his daughter with whom I dwelt (whoſe name was <hi>Franciſco Lopus</hi>) hauing good ſkill in Phiſicke, came daily to my chamber, &amp; there let mée blood, purged, and dieted me, giuing his daughter in charge not to let me want any thing, by whoſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and tender vſage, it pleaſed God to reſtore mée to my health and ſtrength againe. There in <hi>Coro</hi> two of vs died, who was <hi>Thomas Fletcher,</hi> (hee was ſeruant to a ſilke man at the ſigne of the Angell in Cheapſide) and one <hi>Foulke Iones</hi> a ſhoomaker.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Coro</hi> eleuen of vs remayned aliue, beyng all that was left of thrée ſcore and ſeuen, for the ſpace of fiue moneths, euery day going to one another when we plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and often riding into the Countrey, where the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> tooke great delight in our company: for at our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming they would prouide all kind of delicious fruites, which were in moſt abundance in that countrey, and kil Deere, and wild Porks for vs, &amp; would bring vs Apes, Munckyes, Parrats, and any thing that they thought wee delighted in.</p>
            <p>The Countrey there about <hi>Coro</hi> doth yeeld aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Suger, Hony, Ginger and Pitch: Alſo, they haue very good Wheat growing there, but their Bread is altogether made of <hi>Maiz,</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which they haue great plenty: for they reape foure times a yeare. This <hi>Maiz,</hi> they do make it with the iuyce of Suger-Canes, which makes it an excellent kinde of Bread, and it will keepe long as Biſket. Alſo they make their drinke of this
<pb facs="tcp:176940:19"/> 
               <hi>Maiz</hi> and of <hi>Potatos,</hi> which is very ſtrong and ſwéet, for the <hi>Indians</hi> will quickly be druncke therewith.</p>
            <p>Whilſt wee were there, a Spanyard rode into the Countrey to a place of his (with his Brother) to make <hi>Tobacco,</hi> where he had many <hi>Indians</hi> dwelling: one of his chiefe <hi>Indians</hi> (which vſed to bee famyliar with him) took a new Hatchet (which his Maſter had broght with him) and aſked his Maſter what it coſt, &amp; ſuddenly cloue his head therewith, which his brother perceiuing, ran for his Rapier, thinking to reuenge it: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Indian</hi> women had ſtolne it a way before, and ſo they kyld him alſo with their Bowes and Arrowes, and thrée or foure <hi>Negros</hi> which ſeemed to reſiſt them: And thereupon he fled to the Mountayns, gathering a great company vnto him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſing them, that if they would ayde him agaynſt the Spanyards in <hi>Coro,</hi> he would giue them their Wiues &amp; daughters in marriage: But before they put it in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, Captayn <hi>Peroſo,</hi> by a polycie, tooke him feaſting amongſt his fellowes and women, and tooke thirty with him, and brought all to <hi>Coro,</hi> where they were to ſuffer death with great torments, to terrifie the reſt, not to doo the lyke: And of ſome, they cut off their thumbs, and cut the ſinewes of their two fore-fingers, whereby they wanted the benefit of ſhooting.</p>
            <p>Our entertainment was ſuch, that we could not deſire to part from them, to come into our owne countrey, without offending them: For there being a Frigat at <hi>Coro,</hi> redy to go for <hi>Carthagena,</hi> foure of vs made en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty for paſſage, which was <hi>Philip Glaſcocke, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Garrard, William Pickes</hi> and my ſelfe, all the reſt being in the Countrey vpon pleaſure, ſome in one place and ſome in another, and when the Ship was redy to depart, our <hi>Signiours</hi> perſwaded the Gouernour not to let vs go, without he had a Letter from the Vice-Roy,
<pb facs="tcp:176940:20"/> that wee might paſſe in ſafety into Spaine, and ſo for England: and then he ſhewed them a Letter, that it was at our owne choice, whether we would go or tarry: yet becauſe they were loath to part with vs, they willed the Fathers of their churches to tell vs, that if we would ſtay, wee ſhould bee as themſelues, and they would wyllingly beſtow their Daughters and their goods vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs.</p>
            <p>Alſo they told vs, that now England &amp; Spayn were all one in Religion, and that our Sauiour Chriſt came in a Viſion vpon the Croſſe, and appeared before our Kings Maieſtie, and told him that hee was in an error, and byd hym turne, and bee as the Catholickes are, for they are good Chriſtians: and how at the ſight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, three of our chiefe Byſhoppes were ſtrucke into a traunce for the ſpace of three dayes, and after they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered agayne, they preached that they ſhould all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and become Catholickes: adding further, that the King had ſent to the Pope, to ſend learned men into England, to teach their Doctrine aright, which we well perceyued, was onely the ſuggeſtion of their Popiſh Prieſtes, thereby to haue made vs hearken to ther Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: yet notwithſtanding all their allurements on both ſides, our deſire was for our owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: And ſo, three procured meanes for to go.</p>
            <p>But <hi>William Pickes,</hi> by meanes the Gouernour ſaid, that foure was too many to venter in the Ship, was ſtaide.</p>
            <p>So, about the laſt of Aprill, <hi>Philip Glaſcocke, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Garrard,</hi> and my ſelfe, tooke our leaues to depart, leauing all, with whom we dwelt, very ſory: who gaue vs great ſtore of prouiſion for our paſſage, and wept, as though they had parted from their owne brethren and Children.</p>
            <p>They were very loath to let vs go to <hi>Carthagena,</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:176940:20"/> feare we ſhould be put into the Gallyes. And the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Coro</hi> himſelfe, wrote vnto the chiefe men of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> in our commendations. As to <hi>Don Pedro de Barres,</hi> who was his ſonne in Law, but it tooke ſmall effect: for as ſoone as wee arriued there (which was the ſixth of May, within foure dayes after, we were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Pryſon for Spies by the <hi>Tenientie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The x. of May we were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. 1066.</note> for the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was dead, not thrée dayes before we came: yet we carried one Letter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Coro,</hi> written by <hi>Signior Geſper Sanſious,</hi> in our behalf, to <hi>Signior Antonio Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bero,</hi> who prooued a ſpecial friend to vs: for we had not be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an houre in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but he came to vs &amp; comforted vs, &amp; bid vs not to feare, for we ſhould not want any thing wherin he could pleaſure vs: ſo he went to the <hi>Tenientie,</hi> &amp; profered 3. of his <hi>Negros</hi> to ſet vs at lybertie: &amp; if we made an eſcape, he ſhould haue thoſe <hi>Negros</hi> for his owne vſe.</p>
            <p>The woorſt of theſe <hi>Negros</hi> was woorth 300. Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates: but he would not, neither would he allow vs any Victualles.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>Canbero</hi> ſent vs euery day at noone one very good meales meat.</p>
            <p>Alſo, there were thrée Engliſhmen, who ſerued as Marryners in the King of Spaynes Galliounes of Plate, who after that they were at Sea, were by a very great tempeſt of weather dryuen backe agayne to <hi>Carthagena,</hi> in great danger to be ſuncke: for ſhe had twelue foote water within her: ſome of them eſcaped to the <hi>Hauanna,</hi> and fiue of their moſt richeſt Gallionus were in the Shoaldes betwixt <hi>Carthagena</hi> and the <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanna</hi> loſt: theſe thrée Engliſh men did allow vs twelue pence a day, ſo long as wee remayned in priſon.</p>
            <p>Euery Saturday, the <hi>Tenientie</hi> doth ſit vpon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning the Pryſoners, with his <hi>Alcaldes</hi> or Iuſtices.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Tenientie</hi> commaunded, that we ſhould be ſent
<pb facs="tcp:176940:21"/> to the Gallyes. Then one <hi>Alcalde</hi> who was alway found a fauourer of Engliſh men, his name was <hi>Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior Franciſco Lopus de Moralis,</hi> called for our Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which when he had peruſed, he told him that he could not with Iuſtice commit vs. Who anſwered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, Then let them remayne in pryſon, vntil the <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liouns</hi> come from Spaine for the Treaſure.</p>
            <p>Then, within two Moneths after, a Deputy Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was choſen,<note place="margin">Who was Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner alſo.</note> vnto whome a Portyngall (who was our great friend in the pryſon) framed a Petition, which was deliuered by <hi>Iohn Frengham</hi> our Countrey-man. Whoſe Anſwere was to him, that if we could procure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Spaniards to bayle vs for our foorth comming, we ſhould be at liberty.</p>
            <p>Which graunt, <hi>Signiour Franciſco Lopus</hi> and <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio Cambero</hi> had no ſooner heard of, but they entred in Bond of a thouſand Duccates for our foorth-comming.</p>
            <p>The cauſe, why <hi>Franciſco Lopus</hi> did this for vs, was becauſe Captaine <hi>Drake,</hi> when he tooke <hi>Carthagena,</hi> did ſaue all his fathers goods, and his life withall.</p>
            <p>And at our deliuery, the <hi>Tenientie</hi> told vs, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by order of Lawe, they could iuſtly haue put vs to death: Yet ſeing God had ſo myraculouſly ſaued vs, and that wee had indured ſo many miſeries to ſaue our liues, and that onely we came to them for ſuccour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, they were content to ſet vs at libertie.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Franciſco Lopus</hi> brought vs a diſcharge from the Gouernor to the Iayler for our deliuery out of pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and brought vs all thrée to his owne houſe, where was prouided for euery of vs a ſeuerall bedde, for the country is ſo hot, wee cannot lye but one in a bed. Our entertainement was great, and all our ſeruices in plate, with great varietie of meates, and all the moſt delicious
<pb facs="tcp:176940:21"/> 
               <hi>Indians</hi> fruites whatſoeuer, and yet he thought wee neuer fared well, without hee ſent vs one extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary diſh or other from his owne table. Alſo many Gallants reſorted to his houſe to play at Cardes, who would ſhewe themſelues very liberall vnto vs at their winning.</p>
            <p>There wee continued in great pleaſure, vntill the Galliouns were readie to goe for <hi>Spaine</hi> with the treaſure.</p>
            <p>The Citty of <hi>Carthagena</hi> is a place of great force, for by Land, you can not come to it, but one way, which is ſtrongly garded: it is (almoſt) encompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Sea: It hath foure Caſtels, two at the entrance of the Harbour, and one within, where Chaynes are drawne acroſſe the water. The fourth is within the Citty, where their Court of guarde is kept, of 500. Souldiers: and it hath foure Churches.</p>
            <p>The day before we embarqued,<note place="margin">Aug. 25</note> there came two more of our company from <hi>Coro,</hi> which was <hi>Miles Pet</hi> and <hi>Richard Farne. Franciſco Lopus</hi> procured vs paſſage in thrée ſeueral Ships: <hi>Philip Glaſcocke, Miles Pet</hi> and <hi>Richard Farne</hi> in the Ship, called <hi>St. Bartholomew: Richard Garrard,</hi> in <hi>La Madre de Deos:</hi> my ſelfe in <hi>La Santa Cruſe.</hi> So we were a moneth in ſayling to the <hi>Hauanna,</hi> which is neere thrée hundred Leagues from <hi>Carthagena.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sep. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Hauanna,</hi> we liued al aſhore with eightéene pence a day for our dyet.</p>
            <p>It is a place of great ſtrength, for it hath <hi>I.</hi> great Caſtle built vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Rocks at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entrance of the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and another within on the other ſide, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund all the Towne and Harbour: And the thrée within the towne, where <hi>Don Pedro de Valdes</hi> was Gouernor, which was Priſoner in the Tower 1588.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176940:22"/>
            <p>There they victualled the Flat, and watered and repayred their ſhippes, &amp; becauſe they had no victuall to ſerue all the Fléete, they left two ſhips there, the out whereof was that wherein our three men were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, called the <hi>S. Bartholomew:</hi> the other the S. <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</hi> And about the tenth of October, wée departed for <hi>Spaine</hi> by the <hi>Bermouthos,</hi> and ſhot the Gulfe of <hi>Florida</hi> in eight dayes againſt the wind, and ſo w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were nine weekes in ſayling betwixt the <hi>Hauanna,</hi> and the coaſt of <hi>Spaine:</hi> the tempeſt and ſtormes wée had were wonderfull great, in ſo much that all the Fléete were diſperſed, and not aboue two ſhippes did hold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany together, which put them in great feare, leſt they ſhould haue met with the Flemings, who might with thrée good ſhips haue taken all their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with ſmall adoe: for euery little Caruill did put them in feare, thinking her to be a man of warre.</p>
            <p>And within thrée dayes before we came in ſight of <hi>Spaine,</hi> we ouertooke one of the company, which had béene long wanting. And the Maſter of the <hi>Santa Cruſe,</hi> wherein I was, thinking to welcome her with a peale of Ordinance, went himſelf without the ports to charge a peece, and ſuddenly fell into the Sea, and before we could bring the ſhip aſſayes, he was drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>And vpon the fiftenth of <hi>December</hi> wée came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the barre of <hi>Saint Lucas,</hi> but could not enter, becauſe the winde was contrarie. Then came the Gallies out of <hi>Cales,</hi> and towed vs into <hi>Cales,</hi> where they vnloded the treaſure. This made well for vs which were pryſoners: for they were ſo buſie with the Plate, that they neuer regarded vs: for when the Captaine and Souldiours were gone with it, we went aſhore to <hi>Cales</hi> without controulment: And
<pb facs="tcp:176940:22"/> when I thought to haue béene ſecure, the Captaine, with whome I came home by chance, met me in the ſtréete, and called me to him, and ſaid, that I did know how that I was deliuered vnto him as priſoner, and willed me to come to him in <hi>Saint Lucas,</hi> and there he would ſéeke a diſcharge for me. And I promiſed him that I would come: but afterward I feared that hee would haue deliuered me to the Iuſtice; &amp; ſo not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to truſt him, I neuer came in his fight more, but ſought all meanes for my paſſage, which I found har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to get, then when I was in the <hi>Indies:</hi> for our owne Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trimen would anſwer vs, that they would not in danger themſelues, to take vs, without we had a diſcharge from the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſe vncomfortable ſpeeches did much diſmay vs: ſo we remained in <hi>Cales,</hi> in Saint <hi>Lucas,</hi> and in <hi>Siuill,</hi> without any hope of paſſage, one moneth and more, at the charge of <hi>Iohn Frendgeham, Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Gourdon, Ioh Dane,</hi> who was chiefe Trumpeter of the Spaniſh Fléete, and <hi>Iohn Painter,</hi> a Muſician: And at the laſt, (deſpayring of paſſage) M. <hi>Garrard</hi> got paſſage for <hi>Sandwitch:</hi> And my ſelfe made moane to Maſter <hi>Barwicke,</hi> Maſter of a little Ship of <hi>Welles</hi> in <hi>Norfolke,</hi> called, The <hi>George,</hi> who at the firſt word, graunted mée paſſage. So on the ſecond day of February, 1606. hee landed me ſafely at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Downes,</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> giuing me two ſhillings to bring me to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
